Okay
בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף, daf, today's דף daf is יא,
Yud Aleph, eleven. We pick up on the משנה Mishna on the
bottom of י עמוד ב. Yud Amud Bet. So yesterday I wasn't
here, so I was so grateful Michael covers the whole issue about,
I'm sorry, today's דף daf is יא, Yud Aleph, excuse me. Today's
דף daf is יב, Yud Bet, right. That's what I was saying.
As I was saying, today's דף daf is יב, Yud Bet, well,
we pick up on the משנה Mishna on יא עמוד ב. Yud
Aleph Amud Bet. That yesterday Michael covered the whole משנה Mishna on
יא, Yud Aleph, I'm so glad, יא עמוד ב Yud Aleph Amud
Bet about שטרות starot that come to the non-Jewish court, which is
just so fascinating. Number one, because of the monetary documents based on
דינא דמלכותא, dina d'malchusa, and number two because the whole issue of
a גט get and once again עדי מסירה, aidi mesira, that if
it's not signed properly you can still rely on the עדי מסירה
aidi mesira and to what degree did the עדי חתימה aidi chasima
become substitutes for the עדי מסירה aidi mesira and so on. So
very central issues, I should say and I know I'm going back
a little but I just really needed to point out that there's
a, there was one line in the גמרא Gemara there yesterday which
said how can non-Jews sign, it says they are לאו בני כריתות
נינהו, lav bnai krisus ninhu, they're not part of גיטין, Gittin, they're
not, they don't have גיטין Gittin for them so they can't be
part of a גט get that's the idea of כריתות. krisus. And
תוספות Tosafos adds one sentence there on י עמוד ב, Yud Amud
Bet, I'm just going to double back for a minute, where תוספות
Tosafos says, ועל לאו בני כריתות נינהו, v'al lav bnai krisus ninhu,
it just says הוי מטי למפרך הלאו בני עדות נינהו, havi matti
lemafarch halv bnai edus ninhu, right, which is interesting. Well, what do
you mean, how about non-Jews can't sign because they're not כשר עדים?
kosher edim? And actually, it's so interesting how not explicit that is,
that non-Jews are not כשר עדים. kosher edim. I just turned back
one more דף daf on ט עמוד ב, Tet Amud Bet, I
just want to show you, I can't resist this, the תוספות Tosafos
on ט עמוד ב Tet Amud Bet which says אף על פי
שחותמים עובדי כוכבים ומזלות כשרים חוץ מגיטי נשים, af al pi shechosmim
akum kesherim chutz migitei nashim, top תוספות Tosafos on ט עמוד ב.
Tet Amud Bet. תוספות Tosafos says like this, right, why is the
problem with non-Jew signatures on a גט? get? It says ואומר ר"י
v'omer Ri דחותמיהם עובדי כוכבים ומזלות, dechosmeihem akum, why is that not
good on a גט, get, non-Jewish signatures, אף על פי שכתבו ישראל,
af al pi sheksavoy Yisrael, even if a Jew wrote it, so
it's written kosher, דלאו בני כריתות נינהו. delav bnai krisus ninhu. First
what the גמרא Gemara says, they're not part of גיטין Gittin and
therefore they can't make it into a kosher גט. get. I mean,
come on. Number one. ועוד, בעינן לשמה, ve'od, be'inan lishma,
they need to do it לשמה, lishma, ועובדי כוכבים ומזלות אדעתא דנפשיה
קעביד, v'akum ada'ata d'nafshei kavid, we assume a non-Jew doesn't do it
לשמה lishma כדאמרינן בפרק ב. k'd'amrinan b'perek bet. Number two. ועוד, ve'od,
number three, דלאו בני שליחות נינהו, delav bnai shlichus ninhu,
they can't be a שליח, shaliach, דאין שליחות לעובד כוכבים ומזלות. de'ein
shlichus l'akum. And how do you know you need a שליחות? shlichus?
דבעינן שיאמר לסופר לכתוב ולאדים לחתום, debe'inan sheyomar l'sofer lichtov ule'edim lachtom,
we're going to see that the husband has to direct
the סופר sofer to write and the witnesses to sign it, so
that shows that the whole execution of the גט, get, creating of
the גט get is through שליחות. shlichus. So you can't do it
because they're not in the world of גיטין, Gittin, they can't make
a גט, get, they don't do it לשמה, lishma, they can't be
a שליח, shaliach, and then finally reason number four is, he says,
ועוד דפסולים לעדות, ve'od depsulim l'edus, they're פסולים לעדות psulim l'edus ואפילו
רבי מאיר va'afilu Rabbi Meir
and then he tries to prove that they're פסולים לעדות. psulim l'edus.
So it's really quite fascinating how unclear it is that they are
פסולים לעדות. psulim l'edus. תוספות Tosafos needed three reasons to say that
a non-Jew is not kosher to sign a גט get before he
finally said, oh and maybe also they're not a good עד. ed.
So it's just really interesting this idea that I just wanted to
share that obviously the גמרא Gemara assumes if it's written in a
non-Jewish court, of course it's not done according to הלכה, halacha, but
the non-Jewish signatures, it's really interesting the תוספות Tosafos throwing in all
these different reasons. If you need four reasons, it means like none
of them is really a good one, one reason isn't good enough
by itself. Yeah.
For non-Jew the concept of a גט get or divorce would have
been completely meaningless in the time and place of תוספות. Tosafos.
Well that's true also, you mean because of Christians. Right. Yeah, but
I don't know if he was limiting himself to that assumption, but
yes. So let's now continue. So that was the issue about גיטין
Gittin and other שטרות starot that come from non-Jewish courts, and now
we get to the משנה Mishna on
יא עמוד ב. Yud Aleph Amud Bet. האומר תן
גט זה לאשתי ושטר שחרור זה לעבדי,
ha'omer ten
get
ze l'ishti v'shtar shichrur ze l'avdi, this is another way in which
גיטין Gittin and שטר שחרור, shtar shichrur, a writ of manumission might
be the same. Somebody who says, give a גט get to my
wife or this שטר שחרור shtar shichrur to my slave, אם רצה
לחזור בשניהם יחזור דברי רבי מאיר. im ratza lachzor bishnehem yachzor divrei
Rabbi Meir. Rabbi Meir says you can retract either of them before
they're delivered. We don't say that the שליח shaliach
represents the other side, זכין לאדם שלא בפניו, zachin l'adam shelo befanav,
you can't say you automatically are standing in for the wife or
the slave. For the wife it's obviously why not, it's not presumed
a good thing for the wife to be divorced. But for the
slave why not? So we're about to see. Why can't the person
just automatically be seen as a representative of the slave? וחכמים אומרים,
vachachamim omrim, so that's what the sages say. בגיטי נשים, begitei nashim,
that's true by a גט, get, she's not divorced until she gets
it and you can retract. אבל לא בשחרורי עבדים, aval lo bishichrurei
avadim, not by freeing slaves. לפי שזכין
לאדם שלא בפניו, lefi shezachin l'adam shelo befanav, you can
take possession of something for somebody or merit somebody not in their
presence. ואין חבין לו אלא בפניו, ve'ein chavin lo ela befanav, but
if you want to injure them it has to be in their
presence. So you want to divorce- your wife, that's considered an injury
to her, at least possibly an injury to her. So therefore it
has to be given directly to her, or to a person that
she appointed a שליח, shaliach, but not if it's not with her
awareness, whereas by the שחרור shichrur of the slave, that's only a
good thing and therefore even if he's not aware, it's שלא בפניו,
shelo befanav, somebody can represent and stand in for his interests. So
then it continues, שאם רצה, she-im ratza, now how is it clear
that it is only in the slave's interest? Somebody could argue one
minute, the slave benefits because the master is providing him food and
shelter and therefore maybe it's not in his interests to be freed.
So the חכמים chachamim respond and they say the following, שאם רצה
שלא לזון את עבדו she-im ratza shelo lazon et avdo רשאי rashai
ושלא לזון את אשתו ve-shelo lazon et ishto אינו רשאי. eino rashai.
A person, a master could always say I'm not feeding my slave.
So he really doesn't have any legal obligation to feed his slave
even if he does it by custom and practice and so on.
We'll see about that in the גמרא. gemara. So therefore the slave
really only loses by being a slave. He does not even get
a sense that he's entitled to be fed by his master because
that's not true, the master's entitled to say I'm refusing to feed
my slave. But he is not, a husband is not able to
refuse to feed his wife, that's part of the כתובה ketubah obligations
and therefore the wife definitely does lose out minimally the support that
the husband provides, the financial support.
One minute, is there no obligation to feed his slave before he
even is an עבד כנעני?
eved kenaani? This is about an עבד כנעני. eved kenaani. This is
about a non-Jewish slave and we say that that's said about the
animals and that's more like of a מוסר mussar thing and this
is about a legal thing. So we'll see about this, but we'll
see about it in the גמרא, gemara, okay. We'll see if the
גמרא gemara whether we translate this literally or not. Let's finish the
משנה. mishnah. אמר להם, amar lahem, so רבי מאיר rabbi meir said
back, והרי הוא פוסל את עבדו מן התרומה. ve-harei hu posel et
avdo min ha-trumah.
One minute, it's not all benefit for the slave. The slave won't
be able to eat תרומה. terumah. And therefore if he's owned by
a כהן, kohen, now that only addresses the case of being owned
by a כהן, kohen, it doesn't address other cases, but if he's
owned by a כהן kohen he'll lose out because as a slave
he can always buy תרומה terumah cheap or people will give him
leftover תרומה terumah and as a free person not. So there is
some concrete loss that will come to him. And as long as
there's some element of a concrete loss, right, here's the question. Does
רבי מאיר rabbi meir really think in the aggregate it's better to
be a slave or is רבי מאיר's rabbi meir point I don't
care if in the aggregate it's better, if something is not an
unequivocal benefit, if there's an element, if there's some element that is
an injury to a person, then even if in the aggregate it's
clearly in that person's benefit, you cannot represent that person without being
appointed as an agent. Okay, so it could be that he's not
saying that in the aggregate it's better, but he's just saying if
there's something concrete that hurts him then you cannot do it not
in his presence and therefore you can retract before the before the
עבד eved gets the שטר. shtar. כשם שהוא פוסל את אשתו keshem
she-hu posel et ishto and the same way that he if he
was a כהן kohen his wife would lose out if she's divorced
that she would also not be able to eat תרומה. terumah. אמרו
לו, amru lo, they said back to him, מפני שהוא קנינו. mipnei
she-hu kinyano. Yeah, but that's not really relevant because he just owns
him. Okay, so he just owns him, but why is that not
relevant that that's an area that the slave is injured by by
being freed? So we will see about that in the גמרא. gemara.
Michael, you had a question.
Yeah no also I was thinking it makes a big difference potentially
especially if he goes especially if he's married, if he's married to
a שפחה. shifchah.
Yeah, then there's a loss that he loses his wife. That's a
good point too. That's a very point. Well no, there you're thinking
about the עבד עברי. eved ivri. But yes, but it is true
that he will no longer be able to have sex with her
or to live with this woman as a free person. That is
true. That's a very good point. Okay, so now the גמרא gemara
says like this, יתיב רב הונא ורב יצחק בר יוסף קמיה דרבי
ירמיה. yativ rav huna ve-rav yitzchak bar yosef kimei de-rabbi yermiya. רב
הונא rav huna and רב יצחק בר יוסף rav yitzchak bar yosef
were sitting in front of
רבי ירמיה. rabbi yermiya. ורבי ירמיה קא מנמנם. ve-rabbi yermiya ka menamnem.
רבי ירמיה rabbi yermiya was dozing off.
Okay? ויתיב רב הונא וקאמר. ve-yativ rav huna ve-ka-amar. So of course
what do תלמידים talmidim do when their רבי rebbe dozes off? They
talk and learn, right? Okay,
so ויתיב רב הונא וקאמר. ve-yativ rav huna ve-ka-amar. And so רב
הונא rav huna was sitting and saying שמע מינה מדרבנן. shma mina
mi-drabanan. We can infer from the rabbis that say that a person
can represent the slave not in the slave's presence and take the
שטר shtar for him, התופס לבעל חוב במקום שחב לאחרים קנה. ha-tofes
le-baal hov be-makom she-hav le-acherim kana. That if somebody seizes property for
a creditor, the person owns it. Now,
this is before we get to the analogy which is a weak
one which תוספות tosafot questions, let's understand what this case is. Okay,
Michael here owes me ten thousand dollars. You really should not have
borrowed that money, Michael. Anyway, but now okay, what am I going
to do because nobody can find any property that Michael has and
he's been avoiding me? I shouldn't have lent it to you, that's
really true. Okay, so anyway and here and David, I've been telling
all my woes to David and here in a particular case, David
is walking by and he actually sees Michael driving a Jaguar. Now
David loves knows how I've had my eyes on Michael's Jaguar but
I can never find Michael. So David says I am going to
do a favor for Rabbi Linzer and I am going to just
jump in Michael's Jaguar, he left the keys in the ignition and
I will take it for him and I will seize the property
on behalf of the creditor. Okay, you've done me a wonderful favor,
but of course you know at his injury, but he did owe
me the money. Does that work or no? Can you actually grab
property from the debtor for the sake of the creditor, okay, and
does that work? Now if he seized that property on my behalf,
it's not exactly perfect analogy because it has to be real estate,
but okay, whatever, you get the idea. So therefore that's the question.
Now by the way, it might be such a big question because
even though Michael owes me the money and he doesn't owe Dave
the money, and Dave, so it might even be, there's a debate
of רש"י Rashi and תוספות, Tosafot, maybe Dave might not even be
entitled to do it even if I make him a שליח. shaliach.
Like maybe it's something that even only I can do personally or
through the court, but maybe I can't even, you know, do it
through even a שליח. shaliach. So that's, all right, we'll maybe, but
we're not going to discuss that. So the question is does it
work or not? So רב הונא Rav Huna says look, here,
instead I was
giving Michael instead,
well whatever, let's just make me. I gave my שליח shaliach a
גט get to divorce, to free my slave, but I didn't, but
the שליח shaliach just takes it on behalf of the slave. I
didn't say you could take it on behalf of the slave, I
just said you could deliver it to the slave. So that's like
he's seizing my property for the benefit of the slave and it
works, okay? Now תוספות Tosafot points out, wait, wait, wait, that's a
bizarre analogy, like in one case, you know, the guy really owed
me the money, you were seizing it on account of a real
debt that existed, okay? Here I don't owe the slave his freedom,
so how could you seize it from me like essentially seize my
slave from me and I don't owe him like his freedom, what
type of analogy is that? So תוספות Tosafot really grapples with this,
he says well maybe the analogy is I would be freeing my
slave unless it was ultimately paying back for some debt that I
owe the slave, okay? And therefore there's some type of analogy there.
But of course you can't just take the slave סתם, stam, it's
only because I'm in the process of freeing and I've expressed my
will to free the slave. So it's a very strange analogy, okay?
But תוספות Tosafot says maybe the גמרא Gemara somehow does see it
as I've desired to see the slave but not yet, I want
him to get the שטר, shtar, but since I've expressed my desire
and because presumably there's some concrete reason why I'm doing it, maybe
you can jump in and take it, okay? So anyway, that's the
issue of the גמרא. Gemara. But what seems to be bothering the
גמרא, Gemara, the reason it's making this analogy, is because normally when
I say זכין לאדם שלא בפניו, zachin leadam shelo befanav, it is
completely with the will like nobody's standing in the way, okay? Like
a classic example of זכין zachin is I say to David, I
say David like I really want to give Michael this nice iMac
here but he's not around here, why don't you take possession for
him? And I want you to take possession for him. Nobody is,
you're not going against anybody's will, okay? Or you just see this,
you see something on the ground, a מציאה, metziah, and you pick
it up on behalf of somebody else. What makes this case a
little different than a classic זכין zachin is I don't want to
free my slave yet. The very point is as you see in
the משנה, Mishnah, I try to back out a half hour later.
I did want to free him eventually but not yet at this
moment. So by you doing זכין, zachin, you're actually jumping ahead before
I'm ready to make it happen. Right? So the גמרא Gemara sees
it as a type of תופס לבעל חוב, tofes leba'al chov, right,
is that you're grabbing something before actually the other guy is ready
to let go of it. All right, so yes, it's wonderful that
you're זכין, zachin, but it's a little bit against my desire because
I'm not yet fully ready to free the slave. I do want
eventually but not at this moment. Okay? So that's the analogy. So
look, you see that that works, but even though the guy is
resisting, if there's some type of a reason why it has to
happen or it's in the process of happening, either because Michael owes
me the money and you're seizing money he owes me, or because
I've expressed my desire to free my slave just not yet at
this second, that somebody else can jump in and make it happen.
Okay? So that's the idea. All right, so let's take a look.
He says שמע
מינה
shma
mina מדרבנן, midirabbanan, from the Rabbis who say that it works for
the guy to take the possession of the, to stand in for
the slave, התופס לבעל חוב קנה, hatofes leba'al chov kana, that somebody
that seizes money for the creditor, he takes possession of it. אמרי
רב יוסף בר יוסף, Amrei Rav Yosef bar Yosef, Rav Yosef bar
Yosef said, אפילו במקום שחב לאחרים, afilu bemakom shechav leachairim, would that
work even if other people were hurt? Other people meaning not the,
not the debtor.
Meaning when David here is seizing the Ferrari, the problem is that
Michael, he's really seriously in hock, he also owes Charlie money, okay?
And by seizing the Ferrari for me, you're also hurting Charlie's interests,
okay? So how much can you do it on my behalf against
this person's will, even if he owes me the money, if it's
not only hurting him, it's hurting other people? Would you really go
that far?
So he says, אמר ליה
אין, amlei in, yes, I think that that works even if other
people are help. Now is that somewhat similar and maybe again it's
somewhat analogous here because maybe like the owner here is hurt, meaning
because maybe here the owner of the slave is being hurt in
the process, although it's not exactly analogous because that's the same person
you're grabbing. But anyway, okay, yes, I think you can grab something
if somebody owes the money even if other people are being hurt,
and that's what I think is essentially happening in the משנה. Mishna.
The person represents the slave, grabs the slave's freedom even though the
owner is not really yet fully ready to let him go. Okay,
so אדהכי, ad hachi, while they're having this conversation, איתער it'ar רב
ירמיה. Rav Yirmiyah. רב ירמיה Rav Yirmiyah woke up. אמר להו, Amar
lehu, and he said to them, דרדקי, dardakei, children, הכי אמר רב
יוחנן, hachi amar Rav Yochanan, this is what רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan
says, התופס לבעל חוב במקום שחב לאחרים לא קנה. hatofes l'ba'al chov
bimkom shechav l'acherim lo kana. No.
If other people are injured, maybe if Michael only owes me money,
David could do it, but if other people are injured, he cannot
do it. ואם תאמר משנתנו, v'im tomar mishnateinu, what about our משנה?
Mishna? That it seems like you're seizing the slave's freedom for the
slave even though the owner is losing some of his rights, he's
not, you know, he's not yet fully ready to let go. So
the גמרא Gemara says, nope, כל האומר תנו כאומר זכי דמי. kol
ha'omer tnu k'omer zachi dami. When he says "give this to my
slave," giving it to my slave is like he's saying take possession
of it for my slave. So the same way when I say
to David, "David, I want to give my iMac to Michael, take
possession of it for Michael," that works because I'm explicitly asking him
to take possession. When I say "give this to my slave," we
do not say "give" means "give but I don't want it to
be final until my slave gets it." Since I'm giving it to
you and I know that it's possible for you to represent my
slave's interests, that act of handing it over and saying "give it"
is implicitly like giving you the right to take possession right now.
So you're not doing it against my will. We interpret the case,
meaning we never know exactly what the guy's thinking, we have to
make a legal principle. So we interpret the case that when you
give it over and say "give it," that you basically are saying
I am okay if you take possession of it for him at
this moment.
And therefore you can't go back
because, A, David's entitled to represent my slave's interest and, B, he's
not doing it against my interest.
And yet with the wife
you do, you can go back? Yes, because even if I said
זכות, zchut, she's not entitled to represent, I might be okay with
it, but my wife isn't entitled, he's not entitled to represent my
wife, right? So we say the person giving it totally is prepared
for it to happen right now, but the question is, is the
other side, can he represent the other side without them appointing him
a שליח? shliach? And so there's a whole discussion, do we, that
it doesn't seem like we always say תופס לבעל חוב, tofes l'ba'al
chov, you know, in all cases? And he tries to distinguish based
on the specifics of the case.
Okay, so you don't know when the שליח shliach is going to
give it to the slave. It could be one minute later, it
could be a half hour later.
Yeah, but it could be that the slave is halfway around the
globe. So I could be I thought I had time and nevertheless
we don't say that that makes a difference. As soon as you
say "give it," you mean that you're ready to have it, to
have it happen. Okay. I mean if you wanted to wait, you
could
say תן לפלוני עבדי ולא יהא שחרור עד שיגיע לידו. ten l'ploni
avdi v'lo yehei shichrur ad sheyagia leyado. You could, you could stipulate.
But without that, that's how we interpret it legally. Okay. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Now that we've raised this issue of התופס לבעל חוב, hatofes l'ba'al
chov, אמר רב חסדא, amar Rav Chisda, התופס לבעל חוב במקום שחב
לאחרים, hatofes l'ba'al chov bimkom shechav l'acherim, that issue about seizing from
the debtor if other people are being hurt, other interests, תנו מחלוקת
רבי אליעזר ורבנן. tanu machloket Rabbi Eliezer v'Rabbanan. It's a debate of
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and the רבנן. Rabbanan. Now we talk in
the משנה, Mishna, מי שלקט את הפאה ואמר הרי זה לפלוני עני.
mi shelikat et ha'pe'ah v'amar harei zeh l'ploni ani. You're gathering פאה,
pe'ah, you are the בעל הבית, ba'al habayit, and you've left your
corner of your field and you said, you know, but my friend
here, you know, שמעון, Shimon, he's a poor guy and I want
him to get the פאה pe'ah and he's not going to get
around to getting to this field until everybody else has grabbed it,
I will take possession of it for שמעון. Shimon. Okay. So רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer אומר זכה לו. omer zacha lo. That's okay, you
can represent שמעון Shimon and take his פאה pe'ah for him. וחכמים
אומרים יתננו לעני הנמצא ראשון. v'chachamim omrim yitnenu l'ani hanimtzah rishon.
No, שמעון Shimon doesn't own it and the first עני ani that
shows up to the door you have to give it to him.
So that seems to be the debate of התופס לבעל חוב. hatofes
l'ba'al chov. I'm grabbing it on behalf of somebody who's entitled to
it, sort of grabbing it from myself, and he's not exactly a
בעל חוב, ba'al chov, he doesn't, I don't owe, he doesn't have
a personal right to it, but nevertheless, I'm grabbing it on for
his sake, okay, and other people are losing out. And בעל חוב
ba'al chov is sometimes used loosely. Like for example, if there's a
מציאה metziah on the ground, can I pick it up for somebody?
Or is that תופס, tofes, like I picked up this מציאה metziah
for Charlie there, okay? So that's, Charlie isn't a בעל חוב, ba'al
chov, he doesn't have a right to that מציאה, metziah, but I'm
still taking possession of something for someone at the cost to other
people, because now somebody else can't find the מציאה. metziah. Okay. So
that's like a question that gets raised in the beginning of בבא
מציעא. Bava Metzia. So that's what we're saying here. Can you do
this? And here it seems like maybe that's exactly the debate.
So אמר אמימר, amar Amemar, ואיתימא רב פפא, v'itayma Rav Pappa, דילמא
לא היא, dilma lo hi, maybe that's not true. עד כאן לא
קאמר רבי אליעזר התם. ad kan lo ka'amar Rabbi Eliezer hatam. When
did רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer say that you can grab it for
the עני? ani? אלא דמיגו דאי בעי מפקיר ליה לנכסיה והוי עני
וחזי ליה. ela demigo de'ei ba'ei mafkir leh l'nichsei v'havei ani v'chazi
leh. Because you yourself could in theory be in a position to
grab it for yourself. You could declare your entire property ownerless, you
could renounce your ownership of your property, and then you'd be an
עני, ani, you'd be entitled to it. So since you yourself could
take it for yourself, וחזי ליה ומיגו דזכי לנפשיה, v'chazi leh umigo
d'zachi l'nafsheih, since in theory you could take it for yourself, זכי
לחבריה, zachi l'chavreih, he can for somebody else. And like the מציאה
metziah case. The מציאה metziah case is the easiest case that I
can take possession of a מציאה metziah for Charlie and they say,
"Whoa." I'm hurting Michael who was about to grab the מציאה. metziah.
I could've taken it for myself, so of course I can take
it for Charlie. Okay, so here too, in theory, I could've taken
it for myself, I could've been an עני, ani, so maybe that's
why he allows it. But he wouldn't allow it for seizing property
from a debtor where I have no way in which I'm entitled
to that property. Okay? אבל הכא לא, aval hacha lo, but here
maybe in the case of a real debtor maybe it wouldn't work.
That's how רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer could be more lenient by the
עני ani case. And I'll say the reverse. ועד כאן לא קאמרי
רבנן התם, ve'ad kan lo ka'amrei rabanan hatam, and when did the
rabbi, and maybe the rabbis in general say you can seize it
from a debtor, but for the case by the פאה, pe'ah, then
maybe they, that's a specific reason why it doesn't work. עד כאן
לא קאמרי רבנן התם ad kan lo ka'amrei rabanan hatam אלא דכתיב
ela dechtiv לא תלקט, lo telaket, לא תלקט. lo telaket. It says,
you know, את פאת שדך לא תלקט et peat sadecha lo telaket
לעני ולגר תעזוב אותם, le'ani velager ta'azov otam, leave it for the
poor. But we're reading it לא תלקט לעני. lo telaket le'ani. You
are not allowed to gather it for the עני. ani. So we'll
read the פסוק pasuk exactly to exclude this. As a general rule
you can, but here there's a specific exclusion. Okay? לא תלקט לא
לעני, lo telaket lo le'ani, you can't gather it yourself for the
sake of the עני. ani. אבל הכא לא, aval hacha lo, but
in general maybe you can seize it. Okay. So good, so we
haven't proven it from there. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer האי hai לא
תלקט lo telaket מאי עביד ליה? mai avid lei? What does רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer do with לא תלקט לעני? lo telaket le'ani? 'Cause
he says you can seize it for the עני. ani. So מבעי
ליה להזהיר עני על שלו. mibaei lei lehazhir ani al shelo. He
doesn't buy that, like, I don't know, anyway, to say that if
an עני ani has his own field, it's possible you're technically an
עני ani but you still have your small little own field, then
you have to leave פאה pe'ah for other people. You can't keep
it for yourself. Okay. Now. So that anyway was that issue about
the comparison of תופס לבעל חוב, tofes leba'al chov, but what it
really clarified is how can, it's very nice that you can represent
the עבד, eved, who says the master is okay with the עבד
eved being freed right now? And the answer to that is we
say זכות כזכיה דמי. zechut kizechiya dami. Yes, if he's ready to
have, if he's making you an agent to deliver it, it means
we interpret it like he's also prepared to have the slave free
at this moment. Yes.
So when one says there's a זכות zechut for something like in
this case for the עבד, eved, does the person who you appointed
to be the שליח, shaliach, does he have to be on neutral
property or can it even be in your house, like, you know,
is your house like somehow...
No, if it's in his hands, that's a separate רשות. reshut. Okay.
שמא ירצה שלא לזונה. shema yirtzeh shelo lezonah. Now we get to
the actual point that the שליח, shaliach, the slave does not benefit
in any legal way by being a slave because he's not even
entitled, it sounds from the משנה, mishnah, to being fed. You're entitled
to say, I'm not going to feed you. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara is now going to look at this.
שמע מינה, shma mina, says the גמרא, Gemara, we can hear from
this, יכול הרב לומר לעבד עשה עמי ואיני זנך. yachol harav lomar
le'eved asei imi ve'eini zonecha.
The master can say to the slave, work for me and I
refuse to feed you. He has no right, it sounds from the
משנה, mishnah, no, no, excuse me, no obligation to feed his slave.
That's what it sounds like from the משנה. mishnah. The slave gains
nothing from being a slave. So the גמרא Gemara says, is that
really true? So the, now, by the way, you know, again, I
don't know, what was the story actually in slave-owning societies? Did you
have a legal obligation to feed your slave, or was it just
like really dumb not to because you'd be, because of your, you'd
lose your investment in your property? No, the נפקא מינה nafka mina
also would be like if you had an infirm slave. Could you
just like not feed them? Would you be able to be, you
know, would they, I don't know, I don't know what the law
is. But Charlie, something you actually don't know, Charlie? Okay. Anyway.
Well, but
slavery in ancient times was not the same as slavery here
in America, I see.
It was the version here was actually much more draconian. Right.
But slavery they
were property, so you did.
I guess so. Anyway, so it's interesting that in the whole discussion
of the גמרא Gemara whether you have a responsibility to feed your
slaves, it's worth pointing out that it never bases it on a
פסוק. pasuk. It never, it certainly doesn't base it on a contract.
It's not like when you get married that there's some implicit contractual
obligation. Right, it's but almost there's like an implicit, you know, moral
point. And what's really fascinating about this גמרא Gemara is the simple
sense of this משנה mishnah and the simple sense of the evidence
that we're going to sort of line up is going to be
that you don't have a legal obligation to feed your slaves, but
the גמרא Gemara is going to refuse to accept that. And the
גמרא Gemara is going to insist that you do have a legal
obligation to feed your slaves, although it never proves why logically that
should be. So I think that's very interesting, you know, from sort
of like the moral sense of where it's coming from. So anyway,
the גמרא Gemara says, are we supposed to infer from this משנה
mishnah that you don't have a legal obligation to feed your slave?
So the גמרא Gemara says ואיני זנך? ve'eini zonecha? So the גמרא
Gemara says no, הכא במאי
עסקינן, hacha bemai askinan, you do have a legal obligation to feed
your slaves. So what's the case of the משנה? mishnah? דאמר ליה
צא מעשה ידיך במזונותיך. de'amar lei tze ma'asei yadecha bimzonotecha. That
what you can say is although you have a legal obligation to
feed your slave, you can actually get out of it by saying
today I'm not going to feed you and you have to, you
know, feed yourself by your own labor, you know, by what you
earn through your own labor. So meaning I can, you know, I
can I can get out of it by giving him his labor
for that day back to him and allowing him to use his
own labor to feed himself. Okay. So I can't demand his labor
and not feed him. I can if I'm but if I can
not feed him and then he can have his labor back to
himself, at least for that day or for the period I'm not
feeding him. Now that's why it says the slave doesn't benefit. Because
if the slave how could the slave benefit by being owned? Well
my master has to feed me. But if he only has to
feed you if you work for him, right? So you don't gain
anything by being owned
because I can just because the גמרא Gemara is going to get
to that. I can just say I'm not going to feed you
and work for yourself. Well you know what? That you could do
even if you weren't owned, right? If you- but what do you
gain by being owned, right? You either get fed by working or
not fed by not working. You know what? That's exactly what you
get by not being owned too, right? So therefore there is nothing
to be gained and that's why you know the חכמים Chachamim say
there's no benefit in being a slave. Okay? But it doesn't mean
that I can get work out of you and not feed you.
Alright? הכא במאי עסקינן Hacha bimai askinan what are we talking about?
דאמר ליה צא מעשה ידיך למזונותיך. De'amar lei tze maaseh yadecha limzonotecha.
Go use your own labor to feed yourself. דכוותה סגי De'chavata sagi
the גמרא Gemara says like Michael says דכוותה סגי גבי אשה. De'chavata
sagi gabei isha. So one minute, if that's true we're comparing a
slave to a wife and we're saying a wife does have an
ob- have a benefit of being married. But let's see, by wife
you can say the same thing. דאמר לה צא מעשה ידיך למזונותיך.
De'amar la tze maaseh yadecha limzonotecha. A man can say to his
wife like you know I'm not going to feed you and use
your own labor to feed yourself. So what's the wife's benefit of
being married? I mean you could maybe identify other ones but the
ones that are mentioned in the משנה Mishnah is that she gets
fed. Okay? But that's not true because he could also say I'm
not going to feed you, feed yourself, work for yourself. So the
גמרא Gemara says no. אשה מאי לאו Isha mai lo so why
is it- by a woman why is it- why is it not
considered
a benefit for her to be divorced? Okay? So the גמרא Gemara
says אשה דלא ספקא. Isha de'la safka. No, because by the wife
we could imagine a case where she can't earn enough to feed
herself, okay? And in that case the husband is obligated to pay
the difference, okay? He is entitled to say work for yourself and
feed yourself, but he has to make up any gap. Okay? So
the wife does have a benefit of a financial benefit of being
married. If she cannot earn enough money to provide for herself, right,
the husband has to make up the difference and that is her
financial benefit of being married. So the גמרא Gemara says well what
about a slave in that case? So the גמרא Gemara says עבד
נמי דלא ספק? Eved nami de'la safak?
What about a slave can't earn enough money to feed himself? Does
the master have to feed him in that case? So the גמרא
Gemara says the following. עבדא דנהום כרסיה לא שויא, Avda de'nahom karsei
lo shavya,
so a slave who is not worth the bread of his stomach,
he can't even earn the- you know he can't even work enough,
right? The fundamental reason people men would marry women would not be
because of their labor. Okay? So because of- therefore you can easily
imagine a normal case of marriage where she cannot make a lot
of money through an- through labor, okay? But a slave who can't
earn the fill of his stomach,
למריה למרתיה למאי מתבעי? lemarei lemartei lemai mitbayi? To his master and
his mistress what good is he? Who needs him? Now that's very
nice. Who needs him? But that doesn't mean you don't have a
legal obligation. Okay? So the גמרא Gemara might just be saying well
you- you would have sold him or freed him by then because
who wants the slave like that hanging around? But רש"י Rashi explains
it to mean you actually do not have a legal obligation. Since
the purpose of a slave is for the labor, there is not
a legal obligation to feed a slave if he cannot earn, you
know, if he cannot earn his own keep. Okay? So again, it's
not super, you know, ethical, like you know what happens if a
slave gets sick, right? Do you stop- I mean imagine that, right?
As soon as a slave gets sick, right, okay, it's like, you
know, oh you're sick? Okay, now go ahead and feed yourself. Right?
I mean in theory that's what you could do. דוקא Davka when
he needs the support- needs the support the most, but that's what
it seems to be saying. That you do not have a legal-
you do not have a legal obligation to make up the difference
between, you know, to make sure your- between what your slave cannot
earn and his need to be fed. So therefore there's a definite
benefit of being married, a financial one, which is the husband has
to make sure his wife is fed whether she can earn that
amount of money or not, whereas there's not a benefit of being
slave, because the master has no obligation to make up any difference
if the slave cannot earn his own keep. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this. תא שמע, Ta shema, so we're still
going to try to figure out whether a master has an obligation
to feed his slave. Come and hear. עבד שגלה לערי מקלט, Eved
she'gala le'arei miklat,
a slave killed somebody by- by accident and now he's running away
to the city of refuge. אין רבו חייב לזונו. Ein rabo chayav
le'zono. The- the master can't get any labor out of him there,
I mean I don't know, I guess he could contract him out,
but we're imagining he can't get any labor out of him. Anyway
he has no obligation to feed his slave all the way there
in the ערי מקלט. arei miklat. Okay? ולא עוד, V'lo od, but,
שמעשה ידיו לרבו. she'maaseh yadav l'rabo. Actually if he can get labor
out of him over there in the ערי מקלט, arei miklat, right,
he can hire him out, he's entitled to keep what the slave
earns. So basically it's a משנה Mishnah that's saying you don't have
to feed your slave. I mean it gives an interesting scenario that
he's in an ערי מקלט, arei miklat, okay, but you don't have
to feed him and you're entitled to his labor. So that sounds
exactly to answer the question. So the גמרא Gemara says שמע מינה
יכול הרב לומר לעבד. shema mina yachol larav lomar l'eved. You see
the master can say to the slave, עשה עמי ואיני זנך. asei
imi v'eini zancha. Work for me but I won't feed you. So
that seems pretty clear. So the גמרא Gemara says no. הכא במאי
עסקינן Hacha bimai askinan דאמר ליה צא מעשה ידיך למזונותיך. de'amar lei
tze maaseh yadecha limzonotecha. No, basically if you So if he doesn't
have to feed him, it means that the slave is basically keeps
his earnings to himself, feeds himself with his own earnings. The גמרא
Gemara says one minute, but he didn't say that. It said that
the master is entitled to his earnings. But says, אי הכי מעשה
ידיו למאי לרבו? Ee hachi maaseh yadav lamai lerabbo? So why does
it say that his earnings go to the master? You just got
through saying that he's not feeding him because he's feeding himself through
his own earnings. So the גמרא Gemara says, no, להדפה. lahadafa. What
we mean is is that any money he earns over the cost
of his own food goes to the master. So it's a very
strange משנה. Mishnah. It says the master doesn't have to feed him.
It doesn't mean he doesn't have to feed him. What it means
is the master can tell the slave, earn for yourself and feed
yourself. Okay, that's what it means. And the master gets the slave's
earnings, which means if the slave earns any money over the cost
of the slave's own food, that goes to the master. Very funny
way to say that. It sounds the exact opposite of that. Okay,
anyway. The גמרא Gemara says הדפה פשיטא hadafa peshita obviously. Any money
earned over his own food goes to the master. I mean we
are talking about a slave. So the גמרא Gemara says, no, מהו
דתימא mahu deteima I might have thought, כיון דכי לית ליה לא
יהיב ליה keivan deki lait lei lo yahiv lei since we just
got through saying the master does not have to pay the slave
if the slave doesn't have, can't feed himself, the master doesn't have
to make up the difference, כי אית ליה נמי לא לישקול מיניה,
ki it lei nami lo lishkol minei, so when the slave does
earn money to feed himself, maybe any extra money he gets to
put away like a type of a, you know, of a, of
a, of an insurance, right? So if it's clear that the relationship
to the master is that the master's saying feed yourself, okay, maybe
the slave should be entitled on days that he earns more than
his keep to put that away in a rainy day account to
feed himself for the days that he gets sick or that he's
not able to find labor. That's a pretty reasonable arrangement that I
might have thought. Okay, קמשמע לן kamashmalan that we don't say that.
That it's basically like a day-by-day type of a thing and any
and basically the master can keep any money earned over his own
cost of upkeep and days that the slave can't earn his own
upkeep, tough luck on the slave. Okay, ומאי שנא לערי מקלט? umai
shna le'arei miklat? So why did you give the scenario of ערי
מקלט? arei miklat? This would be true any time. סלקא דעתך אמינא
salka daltakh amina I would have thought to say וחי vechai it
says he will go to one of the ונס אל אחת הערים
האל וחי, venas el achat he'arim ha'el vechai, he'll go to one
of the cities and live, עביד ליה חיותא טפי, avid lei chiyuta
tefei, maybe we have a heightened obligation to ensure that he is
fed and supported, okay, and maybe therefore the master has to feed
him even if he can't earn his own keep. קמשמע לן kamashmalan
that he doesn't. Okay,
והא veha one minute, והא מדקתני סיפא veha midekatni seifa but at
the end of that ברייתא braisa it teaches,
אבל אשה שגלתה לערי מקלט aval isha shegaltah le'arei miklat if a
woman goes to a city of refuge, a wife, בעלה חייב במזונותיה
ba'alah chayav bimezonoteha the husband has to feed her. Okay, so you
see now, when did we say it meant he didn't have to
feed his slave? It meant that his slave could have to, would
feed himself with his own earnings. Okay, but now we're contrasting it
to a wife that he has to feed her. So מכלל דלא
אמר לה, michlal delo amar lah, so when does the husband have
to feed his wife? It's when he did not tell her, you
know, earn your, pay, earn your keep. So דאי אמר לה בעלה
de'ee amar lah ba'alah if he did tell her earn your keep,
אמאי חייב amai chayav why would he have to feed her? So
since he has to feed her, it means that he didn't arrange
it. So מדסיפא דלא אמר לה, midseifa delo amar lah, רישא נמי
דלא אמר ליה, reisha nami delo amar lei, so if in the
end by the wife he didn't make any special arrangement and he
has to feed her, in the beginning where the slave he doesn't
have to feed, it also means that there's no special arrangement.
So רישא נמי דלא אמר ליה. reisha nami delo amar lei. So
the גמרא Gemara says לעולם דאמר ליה. le'olam de'amar lei. No, no,
no, like we've been saying all along. You said to the slave
and you're going to say to the wife, earn your own keep.
So what's the difference between the slave and the wife? ואשה דלא
ספקא ve'isha delo safka like we said before. It's when they're not
earning their own keep. Okay? So the case is, the slave and
the wife are entitled to their own, you know, their own labor.
It says the slave you don't have to feed means you don't
have to make up any difference between what the slave earned and
what he needs for food. The wife you have to feed means
that you do have to make up the difference. So like we're
saying before, taking all of these cases which make it sound like
total פשט pshat is you have no obligation to feed your slave
and we're saying you do have an obligation to feed your slave.
But it means no obligation, it means no obligation to make up
the difference if he can't earn his own keep, whereas by the
wife you have the obligation to make up the difference. One minute.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this, והא מדקתני סיפא veha midekatni seifa one minute, the end
of the משנה Mishnah says, ואם אמר לה צאי מעשה ידיך במזונותיך
ve'im amar lah tzei maaseh yadecha bimezonotayich רשאי rashai
but if the husband says to his wife go earn your own
keep he's allowed. מכלל דרישא דלא אמר לה. michlal dereisha delo amar
lah.
It makes it clear that we're talking that he did not make
a special arrangement. Since the issue of the special arrangement only comes
up at the end of that, so the גמרא Gemara says no,
הכי קאמר. hachi ka'amar. ואי מספקת דאמר לה צאי מעשה ידיך במזונותיך
רשאי. ve'ee misapeket de'amar lah tzei maaseh yadecha bimezonotayich rashai.
Again, completely reading it out of פשט. pshat.
We're always talking... that there was an arrangement. Okay? The first part
says you don't have to feed your slave means you don't have
to make up the difference. You do have to feed your wife
means you have to make up the difference. Then when it says,
oh, but if you made an arrangement it's okay, but we were
always talking about there was an arrangement. So he says, no, no,
no. What that means is if you made the arrangement and she's
feeding herself and she does make up, you know, is able to
fully feed herself, you have no additional obligation. Of course you don't
have any additional obligation. The גמרא Gemara says, so the גמרא Gemara
says, מכלל דמספקת מאי למימרא? michlal demisapeket mai lemimra?
If she's feeding herself, of course. No, מהו דתימא כל כבודה בת
מלך פנימה? mahhu deteyma kol kevuda bat melech penima? Oh, that the
whole honor of the daughter of the king's are in the house.
So therefore, maybe you would actually, your wife would not be obligated,
even if in theory she could find enough work to pay for
her upkeep, you might think that she's only... she doesn't have to
go
knocking door to door and finding that amount of work. Maybe she's
only obligated to take a small amount of work that people are
going to bring it to the house. But actually demand from her
that she does hustles in order to get enough work to pay
for her upkeep, that maybe isn't fair and maybe actually she just,
you know, you should you have to pay for the difference even
if in theory she could earn her upkeep. We can't demand that
of her. We can't demand that she go out and hustle and
do all of that work in order to keep her upkeep. So
the גמרא Gemara says קמשמע לן kamashma lan that we actually do
demand it. Okay? So basically what you have is the following. The
משנה Mishnah said, right? I forget if it's a משנה Mishnah or
a ברייתא. Beraita. Okay? The משנה Mishnah basically said in the case
of the ערי מקלט, arei miklat, right? That was the case. The
משנה Mishnah basically said slave don't feed,
okay?
Wife feed. And then it says, but in the case of wife,
but if you have an arrangement, right? If you made an arrangement,
צאי מעשה ידייך במזונותייך, tzee ma'ase yadeych bimezonotayich,
don't feed. Okay, now this sounds very clear like you don't have
an obligation to feed your slave, right? And come as it... oops.
Okay, so nevertheless, hold on.
All right.
Nevertheless, the גמרא Gemara is very committed to the idea that you
do... that you do have an obligation to feed your slave. So
what the גמרא Gemara is saying is, don't feed means you don't
have to... don't feed means you don't have to... right.
You don't have to make up the difference.
Don't have to...
have
to make up difference.
By the wife you have to make up the difference, okay? Have
to make up difference. Now what does it mean if you have
an arrangement you don't have to feed? You always had an arrangement
here, okay? The arrangement was, you know, feed yourself. So what it
means if you... if you have an arrangement you don't have to
feed means, but if she's able to earn, you know, the full
amount,
then... then no obligation and we don't say, oh no, that's not
fair. Even if she's able to earn the full amount, we're not
going to force her to go out
and to, you know... that's not right for her. She's, you know,
כל כבודה בת מלך פנימה. kol kevuda bat melech penima. No. If
she's able to earn the full amount, she's got to hustle and
go out and earn the full amount and you don't have an
obligation. So we completely re-read this text which clearly is saying that
you don't have an obligation to feed your slave to say that
you do and we're talking about special cases when you've made a
special arrangement here.
So you can't say this is feed yourself and feed me too,
right?
Yeah, he can. Once the slave has earned enough... his wife. Oh,
his wife.
That's...
if he says צאי מעשה ידייך tzee ma'ase yadeych and then I
will... but then I will keep... he might, I think it depends
on whether we say
that
the
תקנה takkanah was for her benefit. So then the answer is that
he's not allowed. But if it was for his benefit, then he
might be allowed to say feed yourself... feed yourself and then any
excess I'm going to... yeah, I'll keep, yeah.
So you're saying it depends or you're saying that...?
I think it depends... I think it depends on how we say
that the תקנה takkanah was made. But this גמרא Gemara seems... seems
to be saying like it was made for his benefit. So it's
made for his benefit, then I think he would be able to
say the first amount you earn you keep, I mean, anyway, he's
going to have to make up the difference anyway, right? And then
beyond that, you know, the money goes to me, yeah.
It's clear from the immediate preceding voice of verse that כל כבודה
בת מלך פנימה kol kevuda bat melech penima is referring to a
non-Jewish woman.
Oh, really? Okay, it's interesting. I didn't even look at that. Okay,
so let's take a look. לימא כתנאי, leima ketannai, let's say this
question is a תנאי tannai debate of תנאי. tannai. אמר רבי שמעון
בן גמליאל אומר, amar Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel omer, יכול עבד לומר
לרבו yachol eved lomar lerabbo בשני בצורת, bishney batzoret,
a slave can say to his master during periods of famine where
where it is hard enough to earn money to feed yourself because
you know there's not enough food to go around. So in those
times of famine, so he can say to him או פרנסני או
הוציאני לחירות. O parneseni o hotziani lcherut. Look, either feed me or
free me. You cannot keep me here without providing enough food for
me. I know it's hard for you, everybody's having a hard time,
it's a famine, but then free me. Okay, he's allowed to say
that to him. Okay, וחכמים אומרים vChachamim omrim the Sages say הרשות
ביד רבו. hareshut byad rabbo. No,
the master is entitled to say I'm sorry I can't feed you
but I'm not going to free you either. So what's going on
here? מאי לאו בהא קמיפלגי, mai lav beha kamiflegi, let's say this
is the debate. דמר סבר יכול לומר, demar savar yachol lomar, one
says you can say to like the וחכמים Chachamim were saying I'm
not going to free you are saying I'm not going to feed
you and you're going to stay on and you're going to work
for me. ומר סבר אינו יכול, umar savar eino yachol, that רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says
no, you're not able to keep him on if you're not feeding
him. So that seems like it's exactly that debate.
דילמא... dilma... I don't know, but anyway the Gemara says ותסברא, vatisbara,
does that make sense that that's what they're debating? והא או פרנסני
או הוציאני לחירות, veha o parneseni o hotziani lcherut, then what does
it mean what's the ultimatum: feed me or free me? It should
be או פרנסני או תן לי מעשי ידי בפרנסתי, o parneseni o
ten li maasei yadai befarnasati, then it should be feed me or
let me not work let me you know let me keep my
own labor. Meaning what's the ultimatum of free me? Free me is
a permanent thing, right? If it was just about the question of
can I demand your work without feeding you, then what the slave
should be saying is listen buddy, if you can't feed me, you
can't make me work today. That's what he should have said.
Okay, but that's not what's going on in this משנה. mishnah. מיבעי
ליה, mibaei leh, should have said. ועוד מאי שנא בשני בצורת, veod
mai shena bishnei vatzoret, why do you have to give a time
of a famine? I mean, I know that that's a nice practical
example but that doesn't have any legal significance to this discussion. אלא
הכא במאי עסקינן, ela hacha bemai askinan, what's the discussion? דאמר ליה
צא מעשה ידיך למזונותיך, damar leh tzei maasei yadecha limzonotecha, we're back
to that. You made an arrangement, okay that's the only way you're
going to be... you're going to be entitled to not feed your
slave if you made an arrangement that he can basically work for
himself. Okay. ובשני בצורת לא ספק, uvishnei vatzoret lo sapak, but the
problem is that arrangement was all nice and good during the normal
rest of the year, but during the... but during the what do
you call it... during the time of a famine, right, before we
said if the slave can't earn his own keep, you're not entitled
to make up the difference, what good of a slave is he?
But here the slave can earn his own keep, except it's a
famine and nobody can buy food now. Okay, so now you have
an arrangement, he's entitled to feed himself, okay, he's earning his own
keep, okay, but in the time of a famine he can't earn
his own keep and he needs you to make up the difference.
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל סבר, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel savar, רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says, או פרנסני או הוציאני
לחירות. O parneseni o hotziani lcherut. Look, right now I'm starving to
death and normally I can earn my own keep but I can't
now, it's not my fault. So either make up the difference or
free me. Why? What's free me going to do? So it says
כי היכי דחזו לי אינשי ומרחמי עלי, ki heichi dechazu li inshi
umerachamei alai, because if you free me and I'm a free person
and I'm starving to death, people will take me in and they'll
feed me and so on. So basically like my life and well-being
is at stake, you can't say I'm not a good slave I
don't earn my own keep, I normally do, right now though like
you know there's nothing I can do about it, so you gotta
help me out or you gotta free me so other people will
help me out. ורבנן סברי, verabbanan savri, and the Rabbis hold, מאן
דמרחם אבני חורי מרחם נמי אעבדי, man demeracheim avnei chori meracheim nami
aavdei, and I wish that that were true. No, you cannot tell
me by freeing you that's going to... I mean look, what the
slave is... the slave is saying is I get that you have
no legal obligation to me, okay, to make up the difference, but
I'm starving to death. So help me out here, at least free
me. And the חכמים Chachamim answer back is no, that's not going
to help you, anybody who would free a starving free person... would
feed a starving
free person would feed a starving slave. And since I don't have
a legal obligation to free
you and since I can say that by freeing you your well-being
is not going to be improved, you know you're not going to
be fed any
better, I'm not forced to free you either free feed. Okay. תא
שמע. ta shema. Anyway, that was a nice way of describing
that debate of explaining that debate. דאמר רב, damar Rav, Rav said,
המקדיש ידי עבדו, hamakdish yedei avdo, אותו עבד לוה ואוכל ואותו פורע.
oto eved loveh veochel veoto poreia. This is a little complicated. So
basically somebody says I am sanctifying the labor of my slave's hands,
okay, which means anything he works automatically goes to הקדש. hekdesh. Now,
okay, let it go to הקדש hekdesh and let me continue to
feed him. The thing is, is that I don't want to feed
him anymore because I'm not getting to keep his labor. So
now
you can say okay if I'm not feeding him, what's he going
to do? He's going to earn for himself and feed himself. The
problem is that what he earns for himself goes to הקדש. hekdesh.
So what... I'm not feeding him and he can't earn for himself,
what's he going to do? So the ברייתא braita says he does...
the משנה mishnah says he does is he borrows money, so that
money isn't הקדש, hekdesh, he uses that money to buy food, he
feeds himself with that money, now he owes... the slave owes somebody
some money. As he's earning now... as he's now working, that labor
goes to pay off the loan. Now the question is how does
the labor go to pay off the loan, doesn't it become הקדש
hekdesh first? Okay, so you could have maybe... That maybe since somebody
essentially has a lien on his labor, it goes to that person
who has the lien before הקדש hekdesh gets their hands on it,
but it doesn't usually work that way. Usually הקדש hekdesh interferes with
liens and הקדש hekdesh will take precedence. So the גמרא Gemara understands
is going to explain, it's not clear from this in the ברייתא
Baraisa but the גמרא's Gemara going to explain what happens is, is
that he basically works like every half of a פרוטה prutah first
gets used to pay off the loan. It's sort of like, which
is a similar way of saying it, but it's not saying that
in principle the lien takes precedence, what it's actually saying is, is
that it's sort of like what's it called a direct deposit or
automatic transfer. Before enough money has been earned that הקדש's hekdesh rights
kick in, הקדש's hekdesh rights kick in only at the פרוטה, prutah,
but at every quarter of a פרוטה prutah or half of a
פרוטה prutah it automatically gets transferred to the creditor. So הקדש hekdesh
never gets their hands on it, okay, that's the way the גמרא's
Gemara going to explain. Anyway, but what you see is, so that's
the scenario. So let's take a look. Okay, לוה ואוכל ועושה ופורע,
loveh v'ochel v'oseh uporeiah, he borrows and he eats and he earns
money and he pays back. שמע מינה יכול הרב לומר לעבד עשה
עמי ואיני זנך. shma mina yachol harav lomar l'eved aseh imi v'eini
zoncha. So how did this arrangement happen? This arrangement happened because the
master basically, you know, is not feeding the slave. So you see
he's able to say work for me and I don't feed you?
So the גמרא Gemara says no, because also if by the master
saying I'm not feeding the slave, think about it for a minute,
if by the master saying to the slave I'm not feeding you,
what would the הלכה halacha be? What if he says I'm not
feeding you, the הלכה halacha would be that the slave's entitled to
his own labor, then how could the master be sanctifying the labor?
Right, you get the scenario? The scenario is that the slave isn't
being fed, that's clear, that's the problem of this ברייתא. Baraisa. But
it's also that the master has sanctified the slave's work. But one
minute, that means that the slave could be not being fed and
entitled to the slave's work. Okay, but we were trying to say
that no, that that's not possible. So you see it is, he
he could not feed the slave and still remain entitled to the
slave's work. So the גמרא Gemara says no, הכא במאי עסקינן במעלה
לו מזונות. hacha b'mai askinan b'ma'aleh lo mezonos. He is feeding the
slave and that's why he's entitled to the work and that's why
he can sanctify the labor. One minute, if he's feeding the slave,
what's the problem, what what has to be solved here?
אי הכי, ei hachi,
says the גמרא, Gemara, למה lamah לוה ואוכל, loveh v'ochel, why's he
bothering borrowing in order to eat since already since he's eating anyway?
So it says להדפה, l'hadafah, no no no, because although the master
is providing bare minimum amount of food for the slave, the slave
wants to eat more to be healthier. So basically the master is
entitled to the work because he's providing—feeding the slave the bare minimum,
he's sanctifying it, okay, but the slave's basically saying look buddy, you're
giving me technically just enough food to entitle you to my labor,
but I'm really not getting the food that I need. So what
am I going to do? So in order to or that I
want. So for that he has to do this whole special arrangement,
okay, but that's why the master's entitled to the labor. So the
גמרא Gemara says ולימא ליה הקדש, v'leima lei hekdesh, so why doesn't
הקדש hekdesh say to him עד השתא סגי לך בלא הדפה והשתא
נמי תסגי לך בלא הדפה? ad hashta sagi lach b'lo hadafah v'hashta
nami tisgi lach b'lo hadafah? Why does הקדש hekdesh to some degree
agree to this arrangement, it's a question why הקדש hekdesh has to
agree, but why didn't הקדש hekdesh say, we're not going to let
you do this trick in order to pay—borrow money and pay off
creditors, do with what your master fed—feeds you, he's feeding you the
bare minimum, you're not allowed to do any trick, all of your
labor goes to us? So the גמרא Gemara says no, הקדש גופיה
ניחא ליה, hekdesh gufeih nicha lei, הקדש hekdesh is happy with this
trick that he's earning a little extra—he's borrowing money and paying it
back and making sure that he's getting extra food. Why's that in
הקדש's hekdesh interest? כי היכי דלישבח, ki heichi d'lishvach, so that he
should be healthy and earn a lot—earn more money. So הקדש hekdesh
is okay, you know, rather than having some oatmeal, he has some
nice, you know, you know, grits and bacon and whatever, you know,
good healthy, you know, breakfast in the morning, and then, so he
borrowed an extra 10 bucks for breakfast, okay, and he'll pay that
back, and now he was able to put in another $100 worth
of labor. So הקדש hekdesh is happy with this trick. Okay fine.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this, כי היכי דלישבח. ki heichi
d'lishvach. Now the גמרא's Gemara going to try to figure this out,
עושה ופורע, oseh uporeiah, fine. So we got it all working out.
The master's entitled to the labor because he's giving him oatmeal, all
right, but we do a whole trick in order to allow him
to eat a little bit more. Now how does this trick work
that after he borrowed money he can be paying back his creditors,
isn't what he's earning הקדש? hekdesh? So the גמרא Gemara says עושה
ופורע, oseh uporeiah, he earns and he pays back, כמה כמה קדשי
ליה, kamah kamah kadshi lei, every bit that he earns becomes sanctified.
So the גמרא Gemara says בפחות פחות משוה פרוטה. b'pachos pachos mishaveh
prutah. No, every amount that's less than a פרוטה prutah it gets
transferred to the creditors, you know again, I don't know does he
have to actually get paid in half פרוטהs prutah or is it
just conceptually we say that they get possession of it? But anyway
every amount less than a פרוטה prutah goes to the creditors before
it becomes sanctified.
הכי נמי מסתברא, hacha nami mistabra, that it makes sense that this
answer that we gave, that you were feeding your slave oatmeal makes
sense. Why, and that that's why you're entitled to the labor, but
generally you're not entitled to the labor if you're not feeding him.
Because רב Rav says, אמר רב המקדיש ידי עבדו, amar Rav hamakdish
yedei avdo, if somebody sanctifies the labor of— The slave's hands, אותו
עבד עושה ואוכל, oto eved oseh v'ochel, the slave is entitled to
eat. Okay? Meaning now that you have sanctified his labor, he's entitled
to eat. Why? Meaning
or which actually means that, that you are not able, well, if
you're not feeding him, basically what Rav's saying is if you're not
feeding him, you're not entitled to his labor.
Okay? דאי לא עבד de'i lo avad because if he's not now
going to work for himself, okay, מאן פרנס ליה, man parnes leh,
who's going to gain his work? It's a very vague statement. Basically
what Rav means
is that
he is entitled to feed, this slave is entitled to feed himself.
And you're not entitled to sanctify his labor unless you are feeding
him. Here the Gemara will,
isn't he usually bow down, isn't he? Yeah, but to work. Okay.
So now the Gemara says like this. Both? Yeah, it's like to
עובד עבודה זרה, oved avodah zarah, okay, to be עובד. oved. So
okay, so the Gemara says to worship or to work, right? Okay.
So Gemara says like this, it's going to spell it out in
the next sentence. אי אמרת בשלמא הכא במעלה ואינו יכול, ei amart
bishlama hacha b'ma'aleh v'eino yachol, the first case was that you fed
him, and you're not entitled to say to the slave אינו יכול,
eino yachol, you can't tell the slave work for me and I
won't feed you. Okay? So you fed him, and that's why you
were entitled to his labor and that's why you were entitled to
sanctify the work. Fine. והא veha and when Rav said basically that
you're not entitled to sanctify your slave's work, is בשאינו מעלה, beshe'eino
ma'aleh, you didn't feed him. So then שפיר, shapir, that works. That
basically we all agree that if you feed him you're entitled, and
if you don't feed him you're not. So the first thing said
you sanctified your slave's labor, that was when you were feeding him.
When Rav said if you sanctified your slave's work, it isn't sanctified,
he's allowed to work and feed himself, that's because you're refusing to
feed him. Okay? So that makes sense. In one case you fed
him, you were entitled to the labor and you sanctified it. When
Rav says if you sanctify the slave's labor, הקדש hekdesh doesn't get
it and he works for himself, that's because you're not feeding him
and you're not entitled to the labor. That all works. Okay. אלא
אי אמרת הכא בשאינו מעלה ויכול, ela ei amart hacha beshe'eino ma'aleh
v'yachol, okay, but if you say that when Rav is saying that
even if you don't feed him, you can say, you know, you
can not feed him and still be entitled to the labor, so
if that's true, if you can, okay, so, אלא אי אמרת התם
ela ei amart hatam that in Rav's case בשאינו מעלה beshe'eino ma'aleh
you're not feeding him, and even if you're not feeding him, יכול,
yachol, you can tell him you still have to work for me.
So then why can he work and feed himself? You're not feeding
him, you're still entitled to his labor and you can still be
מקדיש makdish it. So דאי לא עבד מאן פרנס ליה, de'i lo
avad man parnes leh, if he's not going to work for himself,
who's going to, who's going to enslave him and take his labor?
What do you mean? מאן דבעי ליפסליה, man d'ba'i lifsleh, whoever wants
to can take his labor. Who cares if you're not feeding him?
You're still entitled to the labor. Meaning that Rav's question made it
clear that Rav felt that if you're not feeding him buddy, you
can't keep his labor. And if you're מקדיש makdish his labor to
הקדש hekdesh and he's not being fed, then you weren't able to
be מקדיש makdish that labor. He's entitled to keep it for himself.
So Gemara says that makes it very clear that if you're not
feeding him, right, you are not entitled to his labor. That's Rav's
whole point. So אלא לאו שמע מינה אינו יכול, ela lav shma
mina eino yachol, you are not able to say I'm not going
to feed you and I'll keep your labor. Okay? Because again, what
Rav said is, if you sanctify your slave's labor and you're not
feeding him, he can work for himself. Why is that true? Why
aren't you able to say I'm not going to feed you, I'll
keep your labor? Clearly Rav is saying you can't say that. If
you're not feeding him, you're not entitled to work him. So Gemara
says שמע מינה. shma mina. So you see it's clear that Rav's
position is that you are entitled, you are, that Rav's position is
that you have to feed him and if you're not feeding him,
you're not entitled to his labor. Okay, and now the Gemara's going
to say, even though Rav says that, I know it's almost 8:30,
but I just want to read one more, the Rabbi Yochanan position.
Even though Rav says that you're entitled to not feed him, I
mean you're obligated to feed him, Rabbi Yochanan disagrees. תא שמע. ta
shema. דאמר רבי יוחנן, d'amar Rabbi Yochanan, Rabbi Yochanan says, הקוטע
יד עבדו של חבירו, hakotea yad avdo shel chaveiro, somebody severs, you
know, Reuven severs Shimon's slave's hand. So, so he has to pay
Shimon, he destroyed Shimon's property. Not only does he pay Shimon for
the cost, the injury to the slave, but also נותן שבת ורפואה
לרבו. noten shevet v'refuah lerabo. He also pays Shimon the time that
the slave's in the hospital and he's not working while he's in
the hospital. Because even though by paying him for the cost of
a hand he essentially paid him for all of the field, all
of the labor he's not going to get for the next 20
years of working in the field, but even the two months he's
in the hospital, he's not doing other type of work. He's not
baby-sitting. There's other work he could do, right, even with a hand
being missing, that he's not doing while he's in the hospital. That's
called שבת, shevet, the amount of labor he's not doing just because
he's in the hospital, not because he lost the hand. Right. And
that also goes to Shimon. Okay? And רפואה... refuah... So the doctor
bills go to שמעון. Shimon. We'll see about doctor bills in a
minute. ורבו. Vrabo. ואותו עבד ניזון מן הצדקה. v'oso eved nizon min
hatzedaka. But now, who is feeding the slave? Oh, that's coming from
צדקה tzedaka funds. Okay, because the master isn't getting any work out
of him. So it's coming from צדקה tzedaka funds. So the גמרא
Gemara says, why is it coming from צדקה tzedaka funds? According to
רב, Rav, you should be obligated to feed your slave, to work,
you're getting paid for your slave's work, that's שבת. shevet. Right? So
if you're getting paid for your slave's work, you should be feeding
him. But רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says no, you could be getting
paid for your slave's work, the שבת, shevet, and not feeding him.
שמע מינה shma mina that you see according to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi
Yochanan, יכול הרב לומר לעבד, yakhol harav lomar l'eved, the master can
say to the slave, עשה עמי ואיני זונך, asei imi v'eini zonkha,
work for me, I'm keeping your שבת shevet payments, and I'm not
going to feed you. גמרא Gemara says no, הכא במאי עסקינן במעלה
לו מזונות. hakha b'mai askinan b'mala lo mezonot. No no no. We're
talking about that he is feeding him. So what do you mean?
If he's feeding him, why is it saying that he's getting fed
from צדקה? tzedaka? So it says אי הכי אמאי ניזון מן הצדקה,
ihakhi amai nizon min hatzedaka, what does it mean he's being fed
from צדקה? tzedaka? So then we're going to try to say להדפה.
l'hadapa. No no no. You're feeding your slave oatmeal in the hospital
and you're getting his שבת shevet money. Oh but צדקה tzedaka pays
for more food, okay, beyond the bare minimum. גמרא Gemara says one
minute. אי הכי, ihakhi, ניזון. nizon. ניזון nizon means bare, the bare
sustenance food. Okay, and it says ניזון מן הצדקה. nizon min hatzedaka.
According to you that צדקה tzedaka is paying for the better meal
plan, so מתפרנס מיבעי ליה. mitparnes mibaye lei. The word מתפרנס mitparnes
means a level of sustenance beyond ניזון. nizon. ניזון מן הצדקה nizon
min hatzedaka means the bare minimum meal plan. So it's clear from
רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan teaching that you are not paying even the
bare minimum for his food and nevertheless you're getting his שבת shevet
payments, his work payments. אלא לאו שמע מינה ela lav shma mina
you see according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan he argues on רב,
Rav, יכול שמע מינה yakhol shma mina that you are able. And
one wonders if it's basically a בבלי-ארץ ישראל debate. I don't know
enough about slaves in the Sassanian Empire, but anyway, רב Rav is
saying that you are not entitled to his labor if you're not
feeding him, and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says you are. I can
have צדקה tzedaka pay his bills, pay his hospital bills, and I'll
still keep the שבת. shevet. Or whatever and I'll still keep his
food bills and I'll still keep the שבת. shevet. And let's just
read one more sentence here to wrap up this teaching. אמר מר,
amar mar, נותנין שבתו ורפואתו לרבו. nosin shivto u'refuaso l'rabo. You give
the שבת shevet to the master, and the money, and the רפואה.
refuah. The money he's not earning because he's in the hospital. שבתו
פשיטא, shivto pshita, obviously the master gets the שבת, shevet, that's his
labor. ורפואתו איצטריכא. urefuaso itztrikha. No no no. You give, you pay
the doctor bills to the master. So the גמרא Gemara says, why
pay the doctor bills to the master? If שמעון Shimon who if
ראובן Reuven cut off the hand, he should be paying the doctor
bills to the hospital. So the גמרא Gemara says, רפואתו דידיה היא.
refuaso didei hi. Wait minute, the money for the doctor bills goes
to the slave, דבעי איתסויי ביה, d'bai isiyei beh, he has to
get healed with it, meaning it goes to the slave so he
can pay the doctors. Why does it go to the master? So
the גמרא Gemara says, לא צריכא דאמדו ליה לחמישה יומי. lo tzerikha
d'amdu lei l'chamisha yomei. Basically they said, it's going to take you
five days to recuperate. Okay, so here's the money for five days
of a hospital stay or for five days, five days of doctor's
treatment. But ועבדו ליה סמא חריפא ואיתסי בתלתא יומי, v'avdu lei samakh
kharifa v'itzi bitlasa yomei, but they did some very vigorous type of
a medicine and he managed to be healed in three days. Okay,
but it came at what cost? It came at the cost of
a little suffering to the slave himself. It was hard on the
slave, but it saved him two days of hospital bills. Okay, so
who gets to pocket those extra two days? Because when the injury
was occurred we assessed a five-day payment of hospital bills that ראובן.
Reuven.
Is it based on what happened?
No, apparently not, that's a whole סוגיה sugya in בבא קמא, Bava
Kama, but apparently not.
So we assessed for five-day payment on ראובן, Reuven, the slave agreed
to do something harsher and he saved himself two days in the
hospital. So the hospital only got three of those payments, who pockets
the difference? So מהו דתימא, mah d'teima, I might think צערא דידיה
הוא, tzaara didei hu, that the slave suffered and therefore the slave
pockets it. קמשמע לן kamashma lan that no, the master's entitled to
everything. The same way the master's entitled to the sweat and the
hard work of the slave in general. If the slave earned money
by suffering with this harder form of treatment, the master gets to
pocket it. Okay, so anyway we have now ended the discussion of
whether you can say to your slave work for me and I
won't feed you. That רב Rav says you cannot say that, you
have to feed him or he's able to work for himself. And
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says you have no legal obligation to feed
your slave. Okay, we have that debate. And now we're going either
way, it's not in the slave's interest to be owned, because even
if you're not entitled to work him without feeding him, you could
have him just feed himself and you don't have to pay the
difference. So either way is the חכמים's Chakhamim position that he's not
better off being owned and we're going to continue tomorrow to see
רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir position of saying it's still not an absolute
benefit for him to be free, so we'll continue with that debate,
but at least we've wrapped up this סוגיה sugya about עשה עמי
ואיני זונך. asei imi v'eini zonkha. Alright, good.